<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The bloody dovvnfall of adultery. murder, ambition at the end of which are added Westons, and Mistris Turners last teares, shed for the murder of Sir Thomas Ouerbury poysoned in the Tower; who for the fact, suffered deserued execution at Tiburne the 14. of Nouember last. 1615.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1615</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08608</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18919.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113551</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848784</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848784</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13898</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08608)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13898)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1148:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The bloody dovvnfall of adultery. murder, ambition at the end of which are added Westons, and Mistris Turners last teares, shed for the murder of Sir Thomas Ouerbury poysoned in the Tower; who for the fact, suffered deserued execution at Tiburne the 14. of Nouember last. 1615.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[30] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By George Eld] for R. H[iggenbotham] and are to be sold at his shop at the Cardinalls Hat without Newgate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1615]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Partly in verse.</note>
                  <note>Printer's and publisher's names and publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>The words "adultery .. ambition," are enclosed in brackets on the title page.</note>
                  <note>With a title-page woodcut.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴ (-A1).</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 18921 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Overbury, Thomas, --  Sir, 1581-1613.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:13898:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Sir Thomas Overbury</figDesc>
                  <head>SIR THOMAS OVERBURY.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13898:1"/>
            <p>The Bloody downfall Of
<list>
                  <item>Adultery.</item>
                  <item>Murder,</item>
                  <item>Ambition,</item>
               </list> At the end of which are added <hi>Weſtons,</hi> and Miſtris <hi>Turners</hi> laſt Teares, ſhed for the Murder of Sir <hi>Thomas Ouerbury</hi> poyſoned in the Tower; who for the fact, ſuffered deſerued execution at Tiburne the 14. of Nouember laſt. 1615.</p>
            <q>Mercy Sweet Jeſus.</q>
            <figure/>
            <p>Printed at London for <hi>R. H.</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the Cardinalls Hat without Newgate.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:13898:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13898:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Bloody downfall of</hi> Adultery, Murder, and Ambition, preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in a black ſeane of Gods iuſt <hi>Iudgements in reuenge of the Inocent</hi> blood lately ſhed in this KINGDOME.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ooking lately into the cuſtomes of this age, &amp; coniecturing the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward affections of men, I gather that the world is the houſe of confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the inhabitants thereof ſet vpon miſchiefe, for the ſeauen Cappitall ſins are growne to ſuch a cuſtome, that our eies want no alurements to bewitch, our eares no perſwayſions to ſeduce, nor our ſences no ſubtlety to affect: Which ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing
<pb facs="tcp:13898:3"/>on the hearts of men, haue brought fourth many pernitious children, to the hurt of Nature, ſome like centaures, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten of clouds: as <hi>Ambition,</hi> ſome like Serpents nurriſhed in dunghils, as <hi>Senſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allity,</hi> ſome like Vapors, rayſed vp to be conſumed as <hi>Flattery,</hi> and ſuch like, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally all dangerous and full of trouble: therefore is it (in the ſence of man) moſt fitting to haue the painting taken off from theſe foule faces, the couers pulled off from theſe cups of Poyſon, and the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert of this bed of Serpents ripped vp, that we may diſcerne what hath long time bene hidden cunningly.</p>
            <p>The firſt that preſents himſelfe vpon our ſtage; will wee call <hi>Ambition,</hi> catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at nothing but Starres, climing onely for Greatneſſe, this is hee, that cunning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly can inuent ſtrattagems to his owne ouer throw, giuing Pens occation to wright Tragedies, if hee riſe from obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, (as many haue done) hee laboreth
<pb facs="tcp:13898:3"/>to be skilfull in thoſe things, which are moſt pleaſing to the greater Sort, and tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable among the commons: His ſtudy is for prayſe, and not for vertue: His lookes like <hi>Manſolus</hi> roumbe, faire and comly without, but within, nothing but rotten bones, and corrupt practiſſes, his aparrell increaſeth with his Fortune, and as worldly affaires direct him, ſo ſuteth hee both faſhions and affections, in his ſtuddy hee affecteth ſingularity, and is proud in being author of a new ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem: if hee chance to come into the eie of the World, hee then creepes into the fauour of ſome great Peerſonage, in fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding whoſe humors (to relieue his wants) makes intruſion into ſome heritage, and matcheth not according to his birth, but to the increaſe of his fortune, and by that meanes, by hooke or crooke, hee atay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to ſome place in the Court: Then begins hee with guifts to winne hearts, by fayned humillity to a voyd hatred,
<pb facs="tcp:13898:4"/>by offices of friendſhip, to bind his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualls, by cunning inſinuations to worke his ſuperiours, by which meanes hee is held to be worthely a Stateſman: being growne to this ſteppe higher, the authority likes him not, without the ſtile, wherein if any croſſe him, looke for poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in his cuppe, or conſpiracy in his walkes, yea ſo peſtilent is his nature, that (like fire raked vp in embers) hee neuer ſheweth but to conſume, both himſelfe and others: if hee perceaue any that by ripe Iudgment conceiteth his courſes, with him hee ioyneth, as if hee ſought his onely protection vnder the wing of his Glory, but the very truth is, hee hath no other intent but this, to clip the wings of his renowne for feare, hee flie beyond him, if the nature of the Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man whom hee enuieth be gentle, hee bringeth him in feare, either of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants in his houſehold, or his familliars that loue his honour, or elſe ſome miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
<pb facs="tcp:13898:4"/>bewixt his Prince and him, ſworne and confirmed by flatteries and intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, till the noble looſeth either his land, authoitie, or place, and hee attaine both his ſtile and promotion: yet plaie hee neuer ſo cunningly, ſuch vncertaine honours beget daily dangers, and makes him careleſſe of his ſoules proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie: For then there entreth into his mind a delightfull ſinne called curioſity, by which to make him more able in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther miſchiefes, hee giues intertainment to witches and charmers, and conſorts him-ſelfe with nouell mongers, and ſtrange inuenters of banquets, to ſet luſt on fire, and that can deuiſe confections to beſot youth with luxury, that for an irefull man can worke ſtrange reuenges, for a fearefull, a ſtrong tower to keepe him in: to be excellent at poyſons, to kill lingringly, like the <hi>Italian:</hi> But againe to our purpoſe, to the <hi>Ambitius</hi> man there is commonly belonging a ruſtick troup,
<pb facs="tcp:13898:5"/>of Flaterers, Bauds, A dulterers, Soothers, and ſuch like, that hating al vertue makes ſin ſeeme pleaſing, which workes in the flexable heart ſuch a ſweet defire of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden pleaſures, that it euen ſurfets and growes ſickes, with exceſſe, Luſt and Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery I meane, which I diſcribe in this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, it is the moſt inſolent of all things, it troubles the mind and taketh away the empire of liberty, it confounds memory, kills prouidence, and treads downe good councel. offends not he the law, that takes poſſeſſion of another mans free hold, and makes a common of his neighboures in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſure, Adulterers I ſay haue no ſpirits to goodnes, nor will they be by any coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell moued to godlines, for their felicity is in the ſurfets of the fleſh, and the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures thereof bring nothing but too deare repentance, the Adulterer ſpights him moſt that examines his proceedings, and plots his ouerthrow that doth but touch
<pb facs="tcp:13898:5"/>his infirmities, Oh! what an enemy is it to Vertue, the onely wrake of wealth, and plaine high way to pouerty. The Adulterer is ſo blinded in heart, and ſo hardened withall, that hee can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly looke vp towards Heauen to behold Gods iuſt Iudgements: yea ſo iuſt and ſure they are, that in all ages this vile ſinne hath beene ſeuerely puniſhed, as by the example of <hi>Iudas,</hi> iuſtice on <hi>Tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat, Dauids</hi> Adultery with <hi>Vrias</hi> Wife, puniſhed in his Sonne <hi>Abſolon,</hi> thouſands of men died in the fields of Moab for this fault, threeſcore thouſand of the children of Iſraell were put to the ſword for the rauiſhing onely a Leuits Wife, of all ſins it is in nature the moſt odious, and brings with it the greateſt ſhame vnto mankind: it is a ſinne that hath made the Earthe drunke with blood, to the confuſion of many Townes and Cities, Sodome and Gomorah were conſumed with fire for
<pb facs="tcp:13898:6"/>Inceſt and Adultery: Troy a proud City made a plow-land for the ſame ſinne: It was the onely adulteries of the French that cauſed a maſſaker of foureſcore thouſand, by the ringing of one bell: Let not the Strumpits eye, ſaies one of the ſages of Greece, ſhine vpon the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of young men, leaſt with the Baſaliſke, it pearce vnto the death: for her malice is as lightning, and more ragine then the ſhe Beare, vpon her at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends malitious hatred, whoſe felicity is onely to reioyce at the harmes of others, giuing more affliction to them that are moſt troubled with affliction, where if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny offend her, ſhe admitts no reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but liues as a partiall Iudge in her owne cauſe, if ſhe heares the aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of vertue then growes ſhe penſiue, &amp; if ſhe want credit amongſt the mighty then falls ſhee working with the meaner ſort, ſhee ſmiles not vppon any man
<pb facs="tcp:13898:6"/>but to be tray him, nor giue him coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance but to vndoe him, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triue, any ſtratagems without Murder, nor dwels by any neighbour but to hurt him, and if ſhee be but croſſed in her will, ſhe euer frets her ſelfe away in anger, and after in Hate and Malice becomes infamous, for her loue is a minet, but her ſpight euerlaſſing, her hand being once dipt in miſchiefe, ſhee neuer walks abroad but in ſuſpition, fearing to bee accuſed by Vertue, and ſtill liues in dread of her good Fortune, yet by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is ſhee ſuch, that ſhee hath courage enough to aduenture on any ſinne, an Ambitious woman ſhewes her ſelfe to bee a troubleſome diſturber of the world, powerfull to make ſmale things great, and great, monſtrous, enuy by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is greeued at the Proſperity of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, hee enuyeth the Great in that hee cannot Equall them, hee enuieth
<pb facs="tcp:13898:7"/>the weake, dreading they ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare themſelues with him: hee enuyeth his Equalls becauſe they ſhould not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come his Companions: in Kingdomes, Common-Wealths, Princes Courtes and Ambitious mens Houſes he is ſtill work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, no Man hunteth after Honor but hee affronts him, onely the miſerable man hee enuies not, becauſe (beeing kept in Priſon) hee feares not his ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, yet hath hee a ſcorne ouer him: Machiuell knowing the venome of this vice, gaue his ſonne this laſt and not leaſt inſtruction: that hee ſhould not bee enui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, but to doe (ſaith hee) ſuch deeds that others may enuy thee, for to bee enuied is the token of good deſert, but to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uious the ſigne of a fooliſh nature, which verefies the ſaying of <hi>Marcus Tullius</hi> the Orator, that the moſt floriſhing for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune is moſt enuied at: But now to bee more familiar in my Diſcourſe, where
<pb facs="tcp:13898:7"/>Ambition, Adultery, Pride, Enuy, Malice, and ſuch like Capitall Sinnes haue ſet in foote, there cannot choſe but follow Mnrder and confuſion, and where the foundation is layd with blood, there can bee a building but of ſmall continuance, but where Honors haue a true beginning, a ground of vertue ſpringing vp by noble deſerts, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued by Wiſedome and maintayned with Care, there cannot chooſe but follow a fruitfull harueſt, and a plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull Winter: contrariwiſe to obtaine ſodaine Honors begets Pride and Vaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory, Pride and Vaine-glory are the cheriſhers of Enuy and Mallice, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy and Mallice the Nurſes of Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and Murder, in which whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer dippeth but the tippe of his ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, giues to his Soule a ſcarlet ſiaine, which neuer can bee cleared vntill the diſſolution of the Body, and then well
<pb facs="tcp:13898:8"/>are they that can waſh it away with the true teares of repentance.</p>
            <p>Brittle is that greatnes that fadeth in a moment, and vaine the ioy that is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſely loſt, hee that hath a ſodaine riſe and can wiſely ſtand, is a moſt happy Worldling, but he that forgets himſelfe on the Pinacle of proſperity is beſotted with arrogancy: therefore let him that hunts for honors in Princes Courts, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in an euen paſſage, for dangerous are the proceedings and buſines of a States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, take this for an example: ſuppoſe that a yong man from the loweſt ebbe of worldly chance haue the aduancement of greatnes laid vppon his ſhoulders, will it not for a time ſeeme a heauy burthen, and a great trouble to his new tranſfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med fortunes? will not the pride of his heart ſwell to a full Sea; euen ready to burſt ouer the bankes of his Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuer? Then rightly may the Picture
<pb facs="tcp:13898:8"/>of Ingratitude bee imprinted in his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front; playing the Viper to his high for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes firſt beginner.</p>
            <p>Beeing thus intituled with State Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, hath he not many ſoothers in ſinne, perſonages of baſe condition attending him, hemming him round with perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of ſelfe conceit, which for a need will venture their liues to gaine him the commands of his will: what becomes of ſuch follies, but a ſorrowfull repentance, and no recouery. All you that haue your hearts pierced with ſad conſiderations, take this for a remembrance of greefe, that is: That when a Woman of noble Parentage, placed on the mountaine of ſmiling chance, hauing the dignity of Greatneſſe ſhining on her fore-head, ſhould humble her ſelfe to baſe conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, giuing her whole mind to malicious hatred, ſecret conſents of iniquity, ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will and wicked proceedings, neuer pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie
<pb facs="tcp:13898:9"/>till the end of damned performan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Oh was not this Woman created for a deep ſorrow to her Aliance, a great greefe vnto her Country, and a foule ſtaine vnto her owne reputation? Is it not alſo a lamentable example, for a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman of good birth and calling, placed in dignity, in high office and charge for his Country, to giue way by conſent to a bloody ſtratagem, and for feare of the diſpleaſures of Greatnes intangles him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the ſnares of reproch? will not this alſo be a continuall remembrance to his poſterity, and a barre of diſgrace branding the coat Armes of his houſe, to haue the common courſe of iuſtice paſſe vppon him in the eye of the multitude. Is it not alſo great pitty that for want of grace ſome of a ſeruile (yet an obſeruing condition) ſhould from the golden meane of low eſtate wait at the elbow of Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and bring fuell to their fire of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb facs="tcp:13898:9"/>wherein at the length they themſelues are likewiſe conſumed. Oh, wherefore ſhould ſimplicity thus blind vp their eyes of vunderſtanding, to bee thus the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſuch dangerous drifts, that aymes at nothing but grudge &amp; mallice? if with <hi>Solons</hi> ſaying, they had ſealed vp their hearts, <hi>Remember the end,</hi> this had neuer beene: then how are they led away with amiſſe, that hauing the guifts of art and experience, the ſecrets of the ſimples of Phiſick, ordained by God for mans good vſe, ſhould by the Diuell and them be conuerted thus to malignant purpoſes, if the feare of God had ſhined in their hearts, it would haue been a light to haue led them from all thoſe darke practiſes, which hath now ſpotted the foreheads of their reputations with the marks of black infamy, ſhame cannot chooſe but be the reward of ſuch enterpriſers, that for the fauors of Greatnes, will dip their hands
<pb facs="tcp:13898:10"/>in the blood of Innocents, and enen as it were worke againſt nature: Oh more then ſauage minded Creatures, in the very deepeneſſe of your blacke and bloody immaginations, (imboldened by whomſoeuer) this might haue been your <hi>Memento,</hi> in which I conclude, that ſtrange and wonderfull are Gods indge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that in theſe fore-paſſed ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems haue ſhined in great glory, ſay you then, that blood innocently ſhed, is layd vp in Heauens Treaſury, not one droppe of it can bee loſt, but lent out to Vſury: water poured forth, ſinkes downe quietly into the earth, but blood ſpilt on the ground, ſprinkles vp to the Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Murder is wide mouthed, and will not let GOD reſt till hee grant re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge, not onely the blood of the ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, but the ſoule of the Innocent aſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his throne, crying out and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming for Iuſtice, which (the Lord bee
<pb facs="tcp:13898:10"/>prayſed) hath beene, and will bee care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully followed by the learned and worthy Magiſtrates of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, whom the Lord God proſper and protect in all their proceedings, to which let all true hearts ſay. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:13898:11"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13898:11"/>
            <head>Miſtris <hi>Turners</hi> Teares, for the Murder of Sir <hi>Thomas Ouerbury</hi> who was poyſoned in the Towre of London.</head>
            <lg>
               <head>1</head>
               <l>IF euer Teares fell from a Wretches eyes,</l>
               <l>I am that Creature: waues on waues do riſe,</l>
               <l>So faſt, and ſwel ſo high they drowne my ſoule,</l>
               <l>In her owne Crimes as numberleſſe as foule.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>2</head>
               <l>Oh had my Cradle beene my ſodaine Graue,</l>
               <l>In Peace my Soule had ſlept, which is a ſlaue</l>
               <l>Now both to ſinne and ſhame: I had not then</l>
               <l>Been of God hated and ſo ſcornd of Men</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13898:12"/>
               <head>3</head>
               <l>Vnhappy was the Wombe that lent me breath,</l>
               <l>Would it had bin the <hi>Charnell-houſe</hi> of Death,</l>
               <l>Had I bin ſtifled there, then had my ſlight</l>
               <l>To Heau'n bin like a Doues, with wings more white.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>4</head>
               <l>O would to God the Day when I was borne,</l>
               <l>Had from the Calender of time beene torne,</l>
               <l>Where now it ſtands accurſed, and does beare</l>
               <l>The marke of a moſt fatall Character.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>5</head>
               <l>Many a Widdow reading there my name,</l>
               <l>Will curſe it, and the leafe that holds the ſame,</l>
               <l>Children as yet vnborne, comming to ſpell,</l>
               <l>Will take it for a Furies name in Hell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>6</head>
               <l>And caſting by the Booke no more will reade,</l>
               <l>But onely learne to heape vppon my head</l>
               <l>VViſhes of miſcheefe though in Graue I lye,</l>
               <l>For to confound mee euerlaſtingly.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13898:12"/>
               <head>7</head>
               <l>But leauing this, let my ſad Story tell,</l>
               <l>Both from what height I fall, &amp; how I fell:</l>
               <l>That though time preſent does not mone my ſtate</l>
               <l>Yet times to come may pitty my hard fate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>8</head>
               <l>My birth was faire, my bringing vp was good,</l>
               <l>My dayes were golden in my widdow hood,</l>
               <l>And might haue been ſo ſtill, but climbers hye,</l>
               <l>Beyond their reach muſt downe, and ſo doe I.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>9</head>
               <l>Plenty and I at board together ſtate,</l>
               <l>I fed with <hi>Diues</hi> dranke in ritcheſt plate:</l>
               <l>VVore ritch attires, taſted all worldly pleaſure,</l>
               <l>But ne're had care to hoord vp head'nly treaſure</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>10</head>
               <l>VVith <hi>Eue</hi> I might haue liu'd in Paradice,</l>
               <l>But that a Serpent did my Soule intice</l>
               <l>To touch forbidden fruit, which reliſh'd well</l>
               <l>In chewing, but be<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng downe it ſmelt of Hell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>11</head>
               <l>Twas not one onely Apple to deuoure,</l>
               <l>For which I long'd: my hunger gap'd at more,</l>
               <l>At a whole tree I look'd: it was a Tree,</l>
               <l>Me thought the goodlieſt mortall eyes could ſee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13898:13"/>
               <head>12</head>
               <l>This Tree I climb'd, and as I pluckt it grew,</l>
               <l>Still freſh and freſh, the boughs were euer new;</l>
               <l>The branches euer greene, buſhy and faire,</l>
               <l>It ſeem'd the Darling both of ſunne and ayre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>13</head>
               <l>But when my Soule lookt vp with open eyes,</l>
               <l>I ſaw the top bough brauing euen the ſkies:</l>
               <l>VVhen the root ſtuck in Hell, where looking in</l>
               <l>I knew it then to be the tree of ſinne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>14</head>
               <l>And though my Conſcience told me I ſhould fall,</l>
               <l>If that I leand to: nothing could appall</l>
               <l>My ſetled reſolution, I would on,</l>
               <l>Though ſtill before me ſtood damnation.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>15</head>
               <l>From this I pluckt the guilded fruit of pride,</l>
               <l>Like Queen-apples they ſhew'd, for euery ſide</l>
               <l>VVas ruddy and alluring, but (what truſt</l>
               <l>Is in vaine earth) being to<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cht they turne to duſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>16</head>
               <l>From this I ſuckt Enchantments which drinke well,</l>
               <l>And luſcious ſweet, yet prou'd the milke of hell,</l>
               <l>Hence did I gather poyſonous drugges to kill</l>
               <l>Such as withſtood my friends, or croſt my wil.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13898:13"/>
               <head>17</head>
               <l>Luſt often lay within my widdowed ſheetes,</l>
               <l>And taught me how to taſt vnbidden ſweetes,</l>
               <l>And that toward hell I might go one ſtep furder</l>
               <l>The laſt and worſt I went into was murder.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>18</head>
               <l>O crying ſinne, which ſmothered nere ſo deep,</l>
               <l>In caues, which ſilent night her ſelfe does keep,</l>
               <l>Bound vp in darknes, like the ſteeme of Hell</l>
               <l>which none can peirce, yet the blaack deed to tell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>19</head>
               <l>Euen graues of dead men rotten long agoe</l>
               <l>VVill open wide: Vengeance walks often ſlow</l>
               <l>To our weak ſight, but when to Strike it ſtands,</l>
               <l>On Heau'ns high Tower, it hath 3 1000. hands.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>20</head>
               <l>Th' Almighties Arrowes fly both ſure &amp; ſtrong</l>
               <l>And where they hit great Oakes fall all along,</l>
               <l>No hidden mark but ſtands within his eic,</l>
               <l>And that he cleaues, when forth his wrath does flie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>21</head>
               <l>Witneſſe my ſelfe and others, who deſying,</l>
               <l>The buſieſt ſearching Sunbeam from diſcrying:</l>
               <l>Where Villany lay lurking, wrapd in cloudes,</l>
               <l>ſo ſafe we thought as dead men in their ſhrouds</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13898:14"/>
               <head>22</head>
               <l>When to Mans Sence twas as impoſible,</l>
               <l>Mountaines to moue, as find a tongue durſt tel</l>
               <l>Our buried plots, See they are rent and torne,</l>
               <l>By Gods leaſt finger; and we left in Scorne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>23</head>
               <l>Our maskes pluckd off our faces now appeare,</l>
               <l>Such as they are indeed, not as they were,</l>
               <l>Plaine on our browes are our cloſe miſchiefes writ</l>
               <l>Who moſt did hide, now moſt diſcouer it.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>24</head>
               <l>The Wolues are caught in ſnares; the ſhepherd now,</l>
               <l>Knows that a Lamb was flain, by whom &amp; how,</l>
               <l>The blood of whom by cruell friend ſo ſpilt,</l>
               <l>Flowes like a Sea, yet waſhes off no guilt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>25</head>
               <l>If any aske mee, why I was ſo led,</l>
               <l>And why ſo neere to hell I ventured,</l>
               <l>I was bewitch'd, for what I did behold,</l>
               <l>Was a moſt bitter <hi>Pill,</hi> but wrap'd in gold.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>26</head>
               <l>That liquoriſh baite intic'd me take it downe,</l>
               <l>As wholeſome Phiſick, but (with ſha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e) tis known</l>
               <l>No poiſon can ſo ſoone deſtroy the <hi>Soule,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The out-ſide glorious, but the inſide foule.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13898:14"/>
               <head>27</head>
               <l>O Gold! thou glittering diuell that confourideſt</l>
               <l>The Richeſt, Faireſt, Strongeſt, wiſeſt, Soundeſt,</l>
               <l>Would God, as He to Indians is vnknowne,</l>
               <l>That ſo their Droffy God were theirs Alone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>28</head>
               <l>Soules would not tumble then ſo faſt to Hell,</l>
               <l>Nor of my Fall ſhould I this Story tell,</l>
               <l>Terror to Soule and Body, had not heauen,</l>
               <l>To Sinnes more high and horrid, pardon giuen.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>29</head>
               <l>Pardon of thee (ſweet <hi>Ieſus</hi>) then I craue,</l>
               <l>What thou haſt Bought and Payd for deerely Saue</l>
               <l>Men let me beg forgiuenes from you too,</l>
               <l>Becauſe I did more then my Sex ſhould doe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>30</head>
               <l>And you of Modeſt dames that be are the note,</l>
               <l>And my black Name quite from your tables blot,</l>
               <l>As I am loſt, ſo let my fault I craue,</l>
               <l>And write Obliuion on my wretched Graue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>31</head>
               <l>You Fathers whom of Children I bereaue,</l>
               <l>You Children whom of Parents I deceaue,</l>
               <l>You Wiues whom Husband les my Guilt does make,</l>
               <l>Forgiue me All: of All this Leaue I take.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13898:15"/>
               <head>32</head>
               <l>Heauen frownes to looke vpon me and my Sin,</l>
               <l>Earth trembles that by her I fed haue bin:</l>
               <l>My very breath poyſons the Aire abont me,</l>
               <l>Hell onely is within me, and without me.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>33</head>
               <l>Yet in deſpite of Hell, from Heauen comes down,</l>
               <l>Mercy I ſee holding a glorious Crown,</l>
               <l>Of immortality ouer my faint head,</l>
               <l>Ieſus in that and thee I'me Comforted.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>34</head>
               <l>Strengthen my weake heart, Death is fearefull grim,</l>
               <l>One finger of thy Hand can vanquiſh him,</l>
               <l>Giue to my fleeting Soule a proſperous gaile;</l>
               <l>That I to Bleſt Ieruſalem may Saile.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:13898:15"/>
            <head>A Prayer made by Miſtris <hi>Turner,</hi> the night <hi>before her Suffering Death.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>VVIth <hi>Mary Magdalene,</hi> I kneele (O <hi>Ieſus</hi>) at thy feete, which I waſh with the teares of a peniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall bleeding heart, dry them vp againe with the Sighes of my afflicted Soule, O my ſweet Sauiour what pretious bloud didſt thou pay in ranſome to fetch my Soule out of euerlaſting Death and Hell? And how (for a golden bribe) haue I ſold that loue of thine, and my owne Saluation? I am vndone for euer, for ſince I could ſpeake the Name of God, or his bleſſed Sonne, I did ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſpeake or doe any thing that was worthy of Heauen. What haue I not beene, that in the world is Euell, and what is now in me, that I dare call Good? My youth was Licentious, my Age wicked, my Latter daies offenſiue and odious to God and Man. Yet notwithſtanding (Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father) Since my Repentant Soule comes crying to Thee for Mercy, as before my Sinnes cryed to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen for Vengeance: bow downe I beſeech thee thine care: dry vp my Sorrowes with thy beames of Grace. I haue not knowne thee, nor neuer reguarded thy Sacred word, yet (O Lord) ſhut me not out of Heauen, becauſe it is a broken, wounded, and oppreſſed heart that knock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth at thy gates of Pitty. Let not my name be blooted out of thy booke of Life, but ſet the Seale on my forehead, that I may be knowne to be one of Thine. I defire not to liue in this World (of which I am weary, as that is of me) but onely in thy Kingdome: to the intent I may change my bloody garments, for a roabe of Immortality: Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort me in my Combat of Death, take diſpaire from mine cies, ſee an Angell to guard me, Help me, Strengthen mee, Haſten me to my home, and let that dwelling be with thee for euer and euer. I come deere Redeemer, I come, into thy bleſſed Hands I commend my Spirit.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:13898:16"/>
            <head>Maſter <hi>VVeſtons</hi> Teares, for the Murder of Sir <hi>Thomas Ouerbury</hi> who was poyſoned in the Towre of London.</head>
            <p>GOD of my Soule and Body, haue mercy vpon mee: the one I haue caſt way by my folly, &amp; the other is likely to periſh in thy Fury, vnleſſe in thy great mercy thou Saue it. My Sinnes are deepe Seas to drowne mee; I am ſwallowed vp in the bottomles Gulph of my owne tranſgreſſions. With <hi>Caine</hi> I haue beene a Murderer, and with <hi>Iudas</hi> a Betrayer of the Innocent. My body is a Slaue to Sathan, and my wretched Soule is deuowred vp by Hell. Black haue bin my thoughts, and blacker, are my deeds. I haue beene the Diuells inſtrument, and am now become the Scorne of Men, a Serpent vpon earth, and an Out-caſt from Heauen. What therefore can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of me (miſerable Catiffe;) if I looke vp to my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, to him I am an Arch Traitor, if upon Earth, it is drowned with Blood of my ſhedding, if into Hell, there I ſee my Conſcience, burning in the Brimſtone lake. God of my Soule and Body haue mercy therefore vpon mee, Saue me, O ſaue me, or elſe I periſh for euer, I die for euer in the world to come, vnleſſe (ſweet Lord) thou catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt my repentant Soule in thine Armes; O ſaue mee, ſaue me, ſaue me.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notice">
            <opener>
               <salute>REaders</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>you that are deſirous to ſee the Reward of the Adulterer and the Adultereſſe, paid by Gods owne hand: there is a little Table, called the <hi>Spectacles,</hi> where you may Read them more at Large.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13898:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
